A Guide to the Historic Fulton Oral History Project, 2011-2012
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Historic Fulton Oral History Project, 2011-2012
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 540
.42 linear feet; 1.3 GB.
The Valentine (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of The Valentine in 2013.
Alternative Form Available
VCU Libraries hosts the streaming digital collection of the Historic Fulton Oral History Project, which can be accessed here.
Historical Information
The purpose of the Historic Fulton Oral History Project is to educate, to raise awareness, and to document life in the Historic Fulton community, located in the East End of Richmond, Virginia. In an effort to document the 20th century history of the neighborhood and its residents, the project collected the oral histories of numerous members of the Historic Fulton community, particularly those with strong ties to neighborhood prior to the city of Richmond's 1970s urban renewal project.
The project was developed in 2011 in partnership among the Virginia Local Initiatives Support Corporation (LISC), The Valentine, the Neighborhood Resource Center of Greater Fulton, and the Greater Fulton Future Legacy Work Team. Physical copies of audio recordings and written transcriptions were distributed to a variety of local institutions to ensure that the oral histories may be accessed widely. VCU is one of those institutions.
Scope and Content
The Historic Fulton Oral History Project contains 17 interviews with 32 named interviewee participants. The interviewees are teachers, activists, clergy, and community leaders who grew up in the predominantly African-American Historic Fulton community from the 1930s through the 1950s.
The interviewees were also witness to the City of Richmond's 1970s urban renewal plan that permanently changed the landscape of Historic Fulton. These interviews allow the members of the community to speak for and about themselves, and therefore they represent a unique perspective on this period in the neighborhood's history With the Greater Historic Fulton area undergoing continued change and development in the 21st century, understanding Historic Fulton's past is an invaluable resource for the neighborhood's future.
The collection includes transcripts of the interviews and mp3 files of the interviews available on CDs or a flash drive. The interviews were conducted by Dr. Caroline Morris. Freda Johnson, the project coordinator, was often present during the interviews as well.
Arrangement
The original order of this collection has been kept.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
The Valentine retains all original oral history project materials and administrative files.
Contents List
- Administrative Information, 2012 (Box-folder 1:1)
  Includes Freda Johnson's autobiographical statement.
- Evelyn Bowman, 29 November 2011 (Box 1:2)
  Interview details: Interview length, 80 min. 55 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Linda Braxton, Pamala Rogers, and Sheila Smith, 12 March 2012 (Box 1:3)
  Interview details: Interview length, 50 min. 47 sec.; Others persons present, Linda Sutton
- Theresita Braxton, 13 March 2012 (Box 1:4)
  Interview details: Interview length, 42 min. 20 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson, Anna (Braxton's caregiver)
- Estelle Braxton-Davis, 19 January 2012 (Box 1:5)
  Interview details: Interview length, 56 min. 57 sec.; Others persons present, Octavia Banks
- Bernadette Tart Clark, 14 February 2012 (Box 1:6)
  Interview details: Interview length, 42 min. 2 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Forrest Dowden, 28 February 2012 (Box 1:7)
  Interview details: Interview length, 66 min.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Ida Ellett, 13 December 2011 (Box 1:8)
  Interview details: Interview length, 49 min. 58 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson, Mary (Pat) Perez
- Alice N. Ellis, Dudley R. Lanthrip, 27 March 2012 (Box 1:9)
  Interview details: Interview length, 82 min. 37 sec.; Others persons present, Rebecca Fralin, Mrs. Ellis's husband
- Carolyn Fuller, 18 January 2012 (Box 1:10)
  Interview details: Interview length, 24 min. 20 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Joseph Highsmith and Annesto Highsmith Younger, 7 February 2012 (Box 1:11)
  Interview details: Interview length, 61 min. 46 sec.
- Larcenia Johnson and Lula Mae Brady, 6 March 2012 (Box 1:12)
  Interview details: Interview length, 39 min. 20 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Milton Johnson, 14 February 2012 (Box 1:13)
  Interview details: Interview length, 45 min. 32 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Raymond Jones, 8 March 2012 (Box 1:14)
  Interview details: Interview length, 35 min. 34 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Blanche Henderson Lewis and Samuel Henderson, Sr., 25 January 2012 (Box 1:15)
  Interview details: Interview length, 102 min. 33 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Mary Patricia Perez, 8 December 2011 (Box 1:16)
  Interview details: Interview length, 64 min. 04 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Linda Sutton, 10 December 2011 (Box 1:17)
  Interview details: Interview length, 56 min. 36 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson
- Fulton Field Interview with Federal Branch, Ephraim Briggs, Wanda Brown, Charles Crawley, Waverly Huges, Patricia Melvin, Eric Robinson, Willie Robinson, and Douglas White, 29 March 2012 (Box 1:18)
  Interview details: Interview length, 97 min. 54 sec.; Others persons present, Freda Johnson and Spencer E. Jones, III
- Interviews on CDs and flash drive, 2012 (Box 1:19)